People Often Speak of Fate. Is It Real?
(Questioner) Nice to meet you!
(Questioner) I have a question
that doesn't have to do with myself.
I often hear people say things like
"That's her fate"
or "He was born with that fate."
I sometimes think maybe
there is such a thing as fate or destiny.
I also wonder whether I could meet
my ancestors in the afterlife.
Some people don't succeed
even when they try so hard
while others succeed without much effort.
This is not about my own life, but..
(Audience Laughter)
When people around me try so hard
but don't get what they want,
they tend to give up.
I listen to a lot of stories like that.
Should I suggest that that's just
their fate and that it wasn't meant to be?
What do you think?
(Questioner) Me? I'm confused.
I don't know.
Then, you can just tell them
that you don't know, either.
If you think there is fate, it exists.
If you don't think there is fate,
then it doesn't.
What's the problem?
(Questioner) I actually am 99% sure
that fate doesn't exist.
But I wanted to ask you, the Venerable
Pomnyun Sunim, for a clear answer.
Everything is made in the mind.
(A saying in Buddhism)
If you think there is such a thing,
there is. If you don't, there isn't.
There could or could not be fate. There is
or there isn't. That's how things are.
(Questioner) I think hearing
a great Sunim's teaching
(Audience Laughter)
instead of my explanation
will help those people more.
That's why I've been waiting here
to speak to you.
Okay. In this world,
do we always get what we want?
(Audience) No. We don't.
Which is normal?
Always getting all our wishes,
not always getting our wishes?
It's normal not getting our wishes
all the time.
Let's talk about rolling the dice
for example.
A dice has 1, 2, 3, 4, 5,
and 6 dots on its 6 sides, right?
So statistically, the chance of getting
the side with 1 is one in six.
So is the chance of getting
the side with 2.
When you roll it, does it always
show numbers from 1, to 2, to 3,
or can it repeat one number many times?
(Audience Laughter)
(Questioner) I guess it sometimes shows
numbers in progression, but some people…
No, I'm not talking about people.
Focus on the dice for now.
Does the dice show numbers in an order,
from 1, then 2, then 3?
Or does it sometimes show 1,
then 1 again, then 1 again?
(Questioner) It's possible
that 1 keeps showing up.
Yes. Things in life are similar
to rolling the dice.
Some people can succeed
over and over again
while others fail over and over again.
Some succeed, then fail,
then succeed again.
Others fail, then succeed,
then fail again. That's life.
If someone succeeds repeatedly
or fails repeatedly,
You can't say that
that's because of their fate.
You can't say their outcomes were
predetermined. It's just pure probability.
The weather forecast doesn't say
it will rain or it won't rain tomorrow.
It gives us percent chance of rain,
as in 60% or 30% chance of rain tomorrow.
(Questioner) Yes
So there's no need to argue about
whether it's fated for things
to work out or not work out.
We have this misconception that
everything should work out as we wish.
When things don't work out, we suffer.
And when we fail repeatedly,
we tend to think it wasn't fated to be.
There are three ways of thinking
about this.
In the West,
who decides how your life goes?
God does.
God's will determines the outcome.
That is why people often blame God
and say, "How can God be so cruel?!"
In India, they believe
that Karma determines everything.
So people there say,
"What did I do in my previous life
that I have to deal with this?
In China, people believe that
your life is determined
by the date and time of your birth.
So they consult the birth signs.
(Questioner) What do you think
about that practice in Korea?
(Questioner) In Korea, we figure out
our fortunes by birth signs too..
I'm saying that originated
from the Chinese tradition.
It's a mix of traditions
from China and India.
When things don't work out,
you blame your fate.
"What did I do in my previous life?"
"How can God do this to me?"
When we say these things,
does it mean we are getting our way?
We don't mention fate
when things work out every once in a while
We blame our fate
when bad things just keep happening.
That all is your subjective belief.
So if you believe fate exists,
then it does. If not, it doesn't.
(Questioner) Okay, I see.
You still don't understand?
(Questioner) Yes, I do understand.
If you believe God exists, God exists.
If you believe God exists, you will see
God manifesting everywhere. Understand?
In contrast, people
who don't believe in God often say:
"How can God let
such a nice person die like that?"
"How can God just let
that person die in a fire?"
If you continue asking these questions,
you'd come to conclude
that God doesn't exist.
But if you ask the same questions to
a person who believes in God, they'd say:
"I almost broke my leg the other day,
but God helped me and I was fine!"
That person will believe
God exists every day.
Even when you're eating or
playing soccer God exists for you.
So it's very, very foolish to argue
whether there is God or not.
Let people choose according
to their own thoughts and beliefs.
Just accept it:
one person can believe one thing
and another person
can believe something else.
All is believable.
Do you see?
If you choose to believe in birth signs,
it seems to make sense, doesn't it?
If you go to a fortune teller,
don't they appear to make sense sometimes?
Nowadays, we have computers
telling us all kinds of things, right?
They all seem to be plausible, no?
They all seem to make sense,
so they persist.
People who go to get their names analyzed-
are they doing that
because their lives are working out?
They are mostly likely people
who are suffering. So they need help.
These name analysts, would they advise
their clients to change their name or not?
They would tell their clients
to change their names
because their clients came to do that.
Would the clients agree
to change their names
If the analysts say that's good for them?
(Questioner)
They would.
So they're helping each other.
We should not judge
whether these beliefs are right or wrong.
There's no need to evaluate them.
If you feel like paying somebody
to change your name, do it.
If you want to go to a fortune teller
for fun, do it.
Don't these things sometimes have
some therapeutic effect? I think so.
When you're down and out and someone
tell you that's because of your name,
You'd feel great immediately
when you change your name.
"Oh, life has been tough
because of my name.."
this could immediately
make you feel better.
So there's no need to argue
whether this is right or wrong.
This is culture.
Cultural practices are neither right
or wrong. Do you understand?
(Questioner) Yes, thank you.
But if we take these things as truth and
become too invested in them, what happens?
We become delusional
and start deceiving others.
Even in Buddhist communities,
some sell good-luck amulets
made of trees struck by lightening.
Or a ceramic jar blessed by a monk.
Or a picture of the great monk Dharma.
All to bring good luck.
We have a lot of advertisements
like that, don't we?
(Questioner) We do.
When life is tough,
people start paying attention to
these things and get tempted by them.
They think, "maybe I should get
one of these things too…"
That's how things like that get sold.
Those sales will contribute to the GDP.
(Audience Laughter)
That's how some people make a living.
(Questioner) I can see that. Thank you.
But there's no need to get
outraged about those things.
It's good not to get deceived
and ripped off easily.
Avoiding things that are too expensive…
There are people on the streets asking
passersby, "Do you know the Dharma?"
Some people get hooked on those
temptations and agree to make rituals
and offerings to their ancestors
with tens of thousands of dollars.
These people pay
exorbitant amount of money..
But what happens when we report
these frauds to authorities?
(Audience) I think we can.
You'd think that'd be a crime, right? No.
If you buy stocks with a lot of money
but they become useless,
can you sue the company? No
Because you chose to put the money in it.
Do you understand?
So the police cannot control
these cult religions.
That would violate the freedom of religion
It is most important for people to be
aware of the truth and not become tempted.
And it's important to realize that
you're not always going to get
what you want out of life.
Getting all that you wish
isn't always a good thing anyway.
We don't know if not getting what we want
could be a good thing ultimately.
Only time can tell.
Life goes up and down.
(Sunim) So there's no need to argue
about the existence of fate or destiny.
(Questioner) I see.
But it's fun. Isn't it?
It's fun to get our palms
read by a fortune teller.
Not arguing whether it's right or wrong,
we can learn about these
as past cultural traditions.
There were foot reading, belly button
reading, face reading, birth sign analysis
Each country has a distinct culture,
right?
So just consider these practices
as cultural components.
In the old days, shamans were considered
part of a religion known as animism.
But today, shamans are considered
rather as elements of the folk culture.
There are shamans who dance
so well on the edges of a giant knife.
They become intangible national
cultural assets these days.
When you look at these things as
cultural expressions, there is no problem.
We just need to be careful of
frauds and con-artists.
Don't give in to these things.
We can recognize that
they are aspects of our culture
and realize people of old days derived
therapeutic meanings from these practices.
I saw a lot of shamans when I was a child.
One time, a friend of mine
drowned and died.
Imagine how much grief his mother was
feeling when her child died so suddenly.
So she went to a shaman who performed a
ritual to save the soul of the dead child.
The shaman put ribbons on a long stick,
swirled it in the lake
where my friend drowned.
Then the shaman picked up
human hair from the water.
They believed that the boy's soul
was saved.
(Audience Laughter)
Then, in a big ceremony,
they sent the dead soul to the afterlife.
The mother must have felt much better
after that, right?
Just telling her to forget about
what happened wouldn't have worked.
But after the ritual cermeony,
she could feel
that her son moved on to a better world.
This is the psychological value
of these practices.
Nobody knows if the boy really
went to a better world or not, right?
(Questioner) Yes.